Jun-ichi Yamada Collection of Bluegrass Recordings
Library of Congress American Folklife Center Archive of Folk Culture
Jun-ichi Yamada collection of bluegrass recordings 1958-1976 1972-1976
AFC 2008/024
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
290 items
approx. 150 manuscripts
137 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in.
1 photographic print: color; 3.25 in. x 4.75 in.
2 artifacts
Yamada, Jun-ichi, collector.
Collection of audio recordings made at various bluegrass festivals and performances in the United States by Jun-ichi Yamada from 1972 to 1976 in Georgia, Illinois, Indiana, Kentucky, Maryland, North Carolina, Pennsylvania, Virginia, and a few other unspecified geographic locations. The festivals include Carlton Haney's Bluegrass Festival at Watermelon Park, Berryville, Virginia; Bluegrass Music Festival in Bluegrass Park, Camp Springs, North Carolina; the Newgrass Festival of 1974; the Wise County Shrine Club Bluegrass Festival; the 2nd Carter Stanley Memorial Festival, McClure, Virginia; the 7th Annual Culpeper Bluegrass and Folk Music Festival, Culpeper, Virginia; Bill Monroe's Bluegrass Festival, Bean Blossom, Indiana; Old Time Family Bluegrass Festival, Callaway, Maryland; Georgia State Bluegrass Music Festival, Lavonia, Georgia; Bluegrass Bonanza Showcase, Indian Springs, Maryland; and the Indian Springs Bluegrass Festival, Hagerstown, Maryland. Instrumentals and songs are performed with banjo, dobro, double bass, guitar, mandolin, and fiddle accompaniment, among other instruments. Tape containers included partial documentation--lists of performers and titles for some tape reels. Collection also includes copies of festival flyers, one photograph, and other ephemera. A few lists and annotations are in Japanese.
Scope and Content
Collection of audio recordings made at various bluegrass festivals and performances in the United States by Jun-ichi Yamada from 1972 to 1976 in Georgia, Illinois, Indiana, Kentucky, Maryland, North Carolina, Pennsylvania, Virginia, and a few other unspecified geographic locations. The festivals include Carlton Haney's Bluegrass Festival at Watermelon Park, Berryville, Virginia; Bluegrass Music Festival in Bluegrass Park, Campsprings, North Carolina; the Newgrass Festival of 1974; the Wise County Shrine Club Bluegrass Festival; the 2nd Carter Stanley Memorial Festival, McClure, Virginia; the 7th Annual Culpeper Bluegrass and Folk Music Festival, Culpeper, Virginia; Bill Monroe's Bluegrass Festival, Bean Blossom, Indiana; Old Time Family Bluegrass Festival, Callaway, Maryland; Georgia State Bluegrass Music Festival, Lavonia, Georgia; Bluegrass Bonanza Showcase, Indiansprings, Maryland; and the Indiansprings Bluegrass Festival, Hagerstown, Maryland. Instrumentals and songs are performed with banjo, dobro, double bass, guitar, mandolin, and fiddle accompaniment, among other instruments. Tape containers included partial documentation--lists of performers and titles for some tape reels. Collection also includes copies of festival flyers, one photograph, and other ephemera. A few lists and annotations are in Japanese.
Various performers including J. D. Crowe, Jim Eanes, Billy Edwards, Bill Emerson, Lester Flatt, Jimmy Gaudreau, Bill Harrell, Tex Logan, Jimmy Martin, Del McCoury, Jesse McReynolds, Jim McReynolds, Bill Monroe, Ricky Skaggs, Red Smiley, Carl Story, Don Stover, Fiddling "Tater" Tate, Cliff Waldron, Doc Watson, Chubby Wise, and Mac Wiseman. Some of the performing groups include Blue Grass Boys, Blue Ridge Boys, Blue Sky Boys, Clinch Mountain Boys, Country Gentlemen, Country Grass, Country Store, Dixie Bluegrass Boys, Dixie Gentlemen, Dixie Pals, II Generation, Lilly Brothers, McCormick Brothers, New Grass Revival, New Shades of Grass, New South, Osborne Brothers, Rice Brothers, Seldom Scene, Shenandoah Cut-Ups, and Sunny Mountain Boys were on the programs for these festivals.
Biographical Note
From 1972 to 1976, Jun-ichi Yamada—a Japanese material scientist and bluegrass enthusiast—recorded various bluegrass concerts and festivals in the eastern United States, ranging as far south as Georgia and as far north as Pennsylvania. It is unknown whether Yamada's time in the U.S. was continuous or periodic. While in the U.S. he stayed with Walter Saunders, an author who contributed articles to Bluegrass Unlimited and wrote liner-notes for bluegrass recordings. He also visited with Marion Kuykendall, the wife of Peter V. ("Pete") Kuykendall—a bluegrass musician, historian, and editor and general manager of Bluegrass Unlimited.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adcock, Eddie; Adcock, Martha; Allen, Red, 1930-1993; Baker, Billy; Baker, Kenny, 1926-2011; Bartenstein, Fred, 1950-; Blackwell, Curtis; Clifton, Bill; Collins, Randall; Duffey, John; Eanes, Jim; Edwards, Billy (Banjoist); Emerson, Bill; Flatt, Lester; Gaudreau, Jimmy; Green, Joe; Harrell, Bill; Keith, Bill, 1939-2015; Logan, Tex; Magaha, Mack; Martin, Benny; Martin, Jimmy; McCoury, Del, 1939-; McReynolds, Jesse; McReynolds, Jim; Monroe, Bill, 1911-1996; Monroe, James, 1953-; Moore, Charlie; Morgan, Tom (Bassist); Rawlings, Bill (Vocalist); Reno, Ronnie; Rice, Tony, 1951-2020; Richardson, Larry (Banjoist); Rowan, Peter, 1942-; Sizemore, Herschel; Skaggs, Ricky; Smiley, Red, 1925-1972; Sparks, Larry; Stanley, Ralph; Story, Carl; Stover, Don, 1928-1996; Stuart, Joe; Tate, Fiddling "Tater"; Trischka, Tony, 1949-; Val, Joe, 1926-1985; Vernon, Bill, 1937-1996; Wakefield, Frank; Waldron, Cliff; Warren, Paul (Fiddler); Watson, Doc; White, Roland; Whitley, Keith; Wise, Chubby; Wiseman, Mac; Wood, Al, 1937-; Yamada, Jun-ichi; Yarbrough, Rual
Subjects
Bluegrass festivals--Georgia.; Bluegrass festivals--Indiana.; Bluegrass festivals--Maryland.; Bluegrass festivals--North Carolina.; Bluegrass festivals--Pennsylvania.; Bluegrass festivals--United States.; Bluegrass festivals--Virginia.; Bluegrass music--1951-1960.; Bluegrass music--1961-1970.; Bluegrass music--1971-1980.; Bluegrass music.; Bluegrass musicians--United States.
Form/Genre
Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: 1. Manuscripts; 2. Sound Recordings; 3. Graphic Materials; 4 Artifacts. Manuscript materials consist of incomplete performer and song title lists that were included in their respective 7 in. reel-to-reel boxes. Sound recordings have retained the original order in which they were received. With one exception (noted in the container list section), the original order grouped recordings together thematically (i.e., by festival, venue, etc.), but not chronologically. Most of the graphic materials were originally located with a sound recording (in a 7 in. reel-to-reel box).
Acquisition
Donated by Hideo Nagai; 2008.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research; access to collection materials may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Finding aid and spreadsheet of information captured from reel-to-reel boxes. (Box-folder 1/1)
    Spreadsheet is organized by sound recording and includes performer and song title list (when available), all hand-written text on each box and reel, media information (brand, physical description, and present condition), and miscellaneous notes.
  - Administrative materials. (Box-folder 1/2)
    Includes the preliminary collection report, shipping labels, customs, and copies of email correspondence between Tōru Mitsui and Michael Taft.
  - Packing lists (printouts of scanned images). (Box-folder 1/3)
    Print-outs of scanned images from the 7 in. reel-to-reel boxes in the collection.
  - Photocopies of housings for audio recordings. (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Manuscript materials accompanying audio recordings. (Box-folder 1/5)
    Includes manuscript materials that document track listings and other information for SR001-SR010, SR017, SR021-SR022, SR033, SR037, SR039, SR045, SR063-SR064, and SR091
  - Flyer for Bill Monroe's 6th Annual Bluegrass Festival in Beanblossom, Indiana, at Brown County Jamboree Park from June 11-18, 1972, with a list of performers. (Box-folder 1/6)
    Includes notices about a barbecue bean day, various contests, and that the camping site has electricity.
  - Flyer for the Fourth Annual Georgia State Bluegrass Festival, July 22 thru July 30, 1972, in Lavonia, Georgia, Shoal Creek Country Music Park, with a list of performers. (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Flyer for the Fall Indian Springs Bluegrass Festival, Indian Springs Campground in Hagerstown, Maryland, Sept. 14-16, 1973, with a list and pictures of performers. (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Flyer in Japanese (which appears to be advertising home security services). (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Kentucky Fried Chicken cardboard advertisements featuring cherry blossom trees., Two copies. (Box-folder 1/10)
- Series 2: Sound Recordings
  NB: All recordings are original with the exception of SR121-137, which are duplications of recordings not made by Yamada.
  - Carlton Haney and John Miller's Berryville Bluegrass Festival (Watermelon Park, Berryville, Virginia), July 7-9, 1972, 9 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR001-009)
    SR043 is a recording of this same festival, and chronologically it comes after SR009.
  - Carlton Haney and John Miller's Berryville Bluegrass Festival (Watermelon Park, Berryville, Virginia), July 5-8, 1973, 7 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR010-016)
  - Carlton Haney and John Miller's Berryville Bluegrass Festival, Watermelon Park, Berryville, Virginia), July 4-7, 1974, 6 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR017-022)
  - Carlton Haney and John Miller's Berryville Bluegrass Festival (Watermelon Park, Berryville, Virginia), July 1-4, 1976, 5 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR023-027)
  - Carlton Haney's Pennsylvania Bluegrass Festival (Crazy Horse Campground, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania), August 18-20, 1972, 8 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR028-035)
  - Carlton Haney's Pennsylvania Bluegrass Festival (Crazy Horse Campground, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania), August 16-18, 1974, 6 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR036-041)
  - Titled "No Where," Indian Springs, Maryland, 1972, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR042)
  - Carlton Haney and John Miller's Berryville Bluegrass Festival (Watermelon Park, Berryville, Virginia), August 1-2, 1972, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR043)
    Continuation of the same festival recorded on SR001-009, and chronologically it comes after SR009.
  - Unidentified, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR044)
  - J. D. Crowe & the New South at Holiday Inn (Lexington, Kentucky), October 24, 1974, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR045)
  - New Grass Festival (Camp Springs, North Carolina), 1974, 6 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR046-051)
  - Bluegrass Music Festival (Camp Springs, North Carolina), September 1-3, 1972, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR052)
  - Bluegrass Music Festival (Camp Springs, North Carolina), September 2-5, 1976, 2 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR053-054)
  - Bluegrass Music Festival (Camp Springs, North Carolina), 1974, 3 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR055-057)
  - The Blue Sky Boys, unidentified location and date., 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR058)
  - The Wise Country Shrine Club Bluegrass Festival (Wise, Virginia), July 3-4, 1975, 3 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR059-061)
  - Carter Stanley Memorial Bluegrass Festival (McClure, Virginia), May 26-28, 1972, 9 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR062-070)
  - J. D. Crowe at the Red Slipper Lounge, 1974, 5 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR071-075)
  - Culpeper Bluegrass Festival (Culpeper, Virginia), June 10-11, 1972, 3 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR076-078)
  - Bill Monroe's Bluegrass Festival (Beanblossom, Indiana), June 11-18, 1972, 5 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR079-083)
  - Old Time Family Bluegrass Festival (Callaway, Maryland), August 24-26, 1973, 9 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR084-092)
  - Georgia State Bluegrass Festival (Lavonia, Georgia), July 22-30, 1972, 7 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR093-099)
  - Indian Springs Bluegrass Festival (Hagerstown, Maryland), September 14-16, 1973, 10 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR107-116)
  - The Country Store at Williams' Restaurant in Virginia, 1974, 2 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR117-118)
  - The Country Store at Red Fox Inn, 1974, 2 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR119-120)
  - Various performers in Camp Springs, (North Carolina), Shade Gap (Pennsylvania), Beanblossom (Indiana), Fairfield (Pennsylvania), and at the University of Illinois, 1958-1969, 9 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR121-129)
    Dubbed from an earlier recording not made by Yamada.
  - Don Reno & Red Smiley (and others) at Camp Springs (North Carolina), Berryville (Virginia), and Shade Gap (Pennsylvania), 1969-1970, 8 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2008/024: SR130-137)
- Series 3: Graphic Materials
  - One 3.25 in. x 4.75 in. color photographic print of an unidentified Asian roofline in the foreground with a skyscraper in the background. (Box-folder 1/11)
- Series 4: Artifacts
  - Two plastic audio tape containers, one each for SR118 and 120, with Japanese handwriting and stamp marks. Loose in box. (Box 1)